Guide to the Isa Glenn and Bayard Schindel Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Isa Glenn and Bayard Schindel papers
1898-1936
YCAL MSS 309
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5
(12 boxes)
The collection consists of material created and accumulated by Isa Glenn and her son, Bayard Schindel, in the course of their literary activities. Material includes typescripts of writings by Glenn and Schindel; correspondence with writers, editors, publishers, literary agents, friends, and family; material relating to Colonel S. J. B. Schindel's military career and to Glenn's travels to the Phillipines and South America; photographs of Schindel likely dating from his time at the Institute for the Harmonious Development of Man at Fontainebleau; and other papers. The bulk of the material relates to Glenn, and sheds light on the trajectory of her literary career and her relationships with other writers in New York during the 1920s and 1930s.
Glenn, Isa, 1874-1951
Schindel, Bayard, 1908-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from E. Wharton & Co. on the Adele Gutman Nathan Theatrical Collection Fund, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Isa Glenn (1874-1951)
Isa Glenn was born in Atlanta, Georgia, where her father, John Thomas Glenn, was mayor for a time. She was a cousin of James McNeill Whistler, and briefly studied art with him in Paris in the late 1890s. In 1903, she married Colonel S. J. Bayard Schindel, and traveled with him to the Philippine Islands, South America, and the South Seas. They had a son, John Bayard Schindel, who was born in 1908.
Upon her husband's death in 1921, Glenn embarked on her literary career. She is the author of several novels, including Heat (1926), Little Pitchers (1927), Southern Charm (1928), Transport (1929), A Short History of Julia (1930), East of Eden (1932), Mr. Darlington's Dangerous Age (1933), and The Little Candle's Beam (1935). Glenn moved in the literary circles of New York during the 1920s and 1930s, and associated with Carl Van Vechten, Ellen Glasgow, Joseph Hergesheimer, Isabel Paterson, Frances Patterson, and Emily Clark. An interest in the teachings of G. I. Gurdjieff led her to befriend A. R. Orage.
Glenn died in 1951, and is buried in Arlington National Cemetary with her husband.
Bayard Schindel (1908-?)
Bayard Schindel was the son of Isa Glenn and S. J. Bayard Schindel. He studied for a time at Gurdjieff's Institute for the Harmonious Development of Man in France, and is the author of The Golden Pilgrimage (1929). He served as a second lieutenant in the Army during the Second World War.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material created and accumulated by Isa Glenn and her son, Bayard Schindel, in the course of their literary activities. Material includes typescripts of writings by Glenn and Schindel; correspondence with writers, editors, publishers, literary agents, friends, and family; material relating to Colonel S. J. B. Schindel's military career and to Glenn's travels to the Phillipines and South America; photographs of Schindel likely dating from his time at the Institute for the Harmonious Development of Man at Fontainebleau; and other papers. The bulk of the material relates to Glenn, and sheds light on the trajectory of her literary career and her relationships with other writers in New York during the 1920s and 1930s.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into two series: I. Isa Glenn Papers, 1898-1936. II. Bayard Schindel Papers, 1924-1932.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Glasgow, Ellen Anderson Gholson, 1873-1945; Glenn, Isa, 1874-1951; Hergesheimer, Joseph, 1880-1954; Johnson, James Weldon, 1871-1938; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956; Orage, A. R. (Alfred Richard), 1873-1934; Paterson, Isabel; Patterson, Frances Taylor; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948; Schindel, Bayard, 1908-; Van Doren, Carl, 1885-1950; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964; Whistler, James McNeill, 1834-1903; Williams, Blanche Colton, 1879-1944; Alfred A. Knopf, Inc
- Isa Glenn Papers, 1898-1936; Series I; 4; (9.5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged into three subseries: Writings, Correspondence, and Other Papers.
  - Writings, 1923-1935
    Arranged in rough chronological order.
    - "James McNeill Whistler...and Some Notes", typescripts, early draft, circa 1923 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "James McNeill Whistler...and Some Notes", typescript, carbon copies, circa 1923 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Synopsis of "The Shuttle", typescripts, 3 copies, circa 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Published Short Stories by Isa Glenn", scrapbook, circa 1923-1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Short Stories to be revised by Isa Glenn", typescripts (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Heat, first copy, typescript, circa 1925 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Heat, printer's setting copy, typescript, circa 1926 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Heat, printer's galley proofs, circa 1926 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Little Pitchers, printer's setting copy, typescript, circa 1927 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Little Pitchers, printer's gallery proofs, circa 1927 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Southern Charm, typescript, circa 1927 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Southern Charm, printer's gallery proofs, circa 1928 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Transport, carbon copy, transcript, circa 1928 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Transport, printer's gallery proofs, circa 1929 (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
    - A Short History of Julia, carbon copy, typescript, circa 1929-1930 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - A Short History of Julia, printer's gallery proofs, circa 1930 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - "First Fever [ East of Eden ]--Connective Tissue", typescript, circa 1928-1931 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - " East of Eden --Connective Tissue", carbon copy, typescript, circa 1928-1932 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - East of Eden, typescript, circa1932 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - East of Eden, 1st version, 1st carbon, typescript, circa 1932 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - East of Eden, 2nd version, 2nd carbon, typescript, circa 1932 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - East of Eden, 3rd version, typescript, circa 1932 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - " Mr. Darlington's Dangerous Age --Connective Tissue", typescript, circa 1933 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Mr. Darlington's Dangerous Age, (1 on cover) typescript, circa 1933 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Mr. Darlington's Dangerous Age, (3 on cover) typescript, circa 1933 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - "Sea Level— by Anne Parrish Reviewed by Isa Glenn", typescript, circa 1934 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - " The Little Candle's Beam --Connective Tissue", typescript, circa 1935 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - The Little Candle's Beam, typescript, circa 1935 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - "Men and Ghosts by Isa Glenn", 22 short stories, typescript, circa 1935 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - "Men and Ghosts by Isa Glenn", only carbon copy, typescript, circa 1935 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - "According to Mac Tavish--Connective Tissue", typescript, circa 1935 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - "Wanted--A Man Who Can Smile", typescript (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1898-1936
    Arranged into two groups: Professional and Personal.
    - Professional
      Arranged alphabetically.
      - Alfred A. Knopf: 5 typed letters (signed), 1928-1931 (Box 8, Folder 34)
      - Baumgarten, Bernice (Brandt & Brandt): 2 typed letters (signed), 1931 (Box 9, Folder 35)
      - Glasgow, Ellen: autograph letter (signed), 1933 (Box 9, Folder 36)
      - Hergesheimer, Joseph: typed letter (signed), 1936 (Box 9, Folder 37)
      - James T. White & Co.: 3 typed letters (signed) and copy of typed letter (signed) from Isa Glenn, 1921-1924 (Box 9, Folder 38)
      - Johnson, James Weldon: autograph letter (signed), 1930 (Box 9, Folder 39)
      - Lane, Allen of John Lane (The Bodley Head): typed letter (signed) and Liveright, Otto: typed letter (signed), 1924, 1931 (Box 9, Folder 40)
      - Mencken, H. L.: typed letter (signed), 1931 (Box 9, Folder 41)
      - Michael, Margaret: typed letter (signed), 1930 (Box 9, Folder 42)
      - Orage, Afred Richard: 7 autograph letters (signed), 1930-1934 (Box 9, Folder 43)
      - Paterson, Isabel [Mary] "Pat": typed letter (signed), 1933 (Box 9, Folder 44)
      - Patterson, Frances Taylor: typed letter (signed), 1923 (Box 9, Folder 45)
      - Pershing, General John J.: 2 typed letters (signed), 1923 (Box 9, Folder 46)
      - Van Doren, Carl: typed letter (signed), 1923 (Box 9, Folder 47)
      - Whistler, James McNeill: cablegram and autograph note (signed), 1898,1899 (Box 9, Folder 48)
      - Wick, Jean: autograph letter (signed), 1929 (Box 9, Folder 49)
      - Williams, Blanche Colton: 2 autograph letters (signed), 1923 (Box 9, Folder 50)
    - Personal
      - Glenn, Helen G. [mother of Isa Glenn]: autograph letter (signed) and Glenn, John Thomas: typed letter (signed), 1923, 1899 (Box 9, Folder 51)
      - Schindel, Bayard: autograph postcard (signed), 5 autograph letters (signed), and 2 cablegrams; 4 autograph postcards (signed), 1927, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 52)
      - Van Saal, Rudie and Virginia; "Aunt Virginia". 5 autograph letters (signed), 1929 (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - Other Papers, 1907, undated
    - Miscellaneous: stiff card, Tiffany & co., calling card, carte-de-visite photograph of Isa Glenn. (Atlanta, GA: Smith & Mote) (Box 9, Folder 54)
    - Additional miscellaneous correspondence from unidentified correspondents, English photography studios, the Chair of the Georgia Society of Colonial Dames of America, etc. (Box 9, Folder 55)
    - Col. S. J. B. Schindel Correspondence and Documents from His Military Career, 1907 (Box 9, Folder 56-57)
    - The Phillipines, printed material (Box 9, Folder 58)
    - Cruise to Rio de Janeiro (souvenirs in an envelope labeled "Rio de Janeiro material"), 1925 (Box 10, Folder 59)
    - Typescripts, Notes on Rio de Janeiro and "The Red Drum" (Box 10, Folder 60)
    - Heraldry, Coat of Arms, 1921 (Box 10, Folder 61)
- Bayard Schindel Papers, 1924-1932; Series II; 1; (2.5 boxes)
  - Writings, 1927, undated
    - "Paul Jones at Sea (short story)," typescript (Box 10, Folder 62)
    - "The Scanty Brunette (short story)," " The Trail of Oedipus (short story)," "The Moaning of the Bar (short story)", circa 1927 (Box 10, Folder 63)
    - "The Little Wars," typescripts and carbons (Box 10, Folder 64)
    - "The Little Wars," typescripts and carbons (Box 11, Folder 65-68)
    - "Plunkett's House," typescript (Box 11, Folder 69)
    - "Why Beelzebub Was on our Solar System," typscript (Box 12, Folder 70)
    - Acting manuscript, incomplete typescript (Box 12, Folder 71)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1932
    - Professional
      - Abdullah, [Captain] Achmed: typed letter (signed), 1929 (Box 12, Folder 72)
      - Balch, Emily Clark: autograph letter (signed), 1929 (Box 12, Folder 73)
      - Baldwin, Faith: autograph postcard (signed); Barnette, Ralph: autograph letter (signed); Baumgarten, Bernice [Brandt & Brandt]: typed letter (signed); Bernstorff, J.: autograph letter (signed) Brown, R.S.: autograph letter (signed); Colquitt, Harriet: typed letter (signed), 1929-1930 (Box 12, Folder 74)
      - Doubleday, Doran: 5 typed letters (signed) with 3 royalty statements, circa1927-1931 (Box 12, Folder 75)
      - Fishburne, Mary: autograph letter signed; Holmes, Calvin: typed letter (signed); Imperial War Museum: typed letter (signed), printed acknowledgment (signed), 1929, 1930, 1930 (Box 12, Folder 76)
      - Johnston, Mary: autograph letter (signed), 1929 (Box 12, Folder 77)
      - Maury, Mrs. M.G.: autographed note (signed), Brookline, Mass--addressed to Isa Glenn, 1929 (Box 12, Folder 78)
      - Orage, A.R.: autograph letter (signed), 1927 (Box 12, Folder 79)
      - Smith, Garland: autograph letter (signed), 1929 (Box 12, Folder 80)
      - Van Vechten, Carl: 2 autograph letters (signed), 1925, 1929 (Box 12, Folder 81)
      - Van Horn, Margaret: autograph letter (signed); Wright, Haidee: Western Union telegram, 1929, 1930 (Box 12, Folder 82)
    - Personal
      - Bundy, Addie H., wife of General Omar Bundy: autograph letter (signed), 1928 (Box 12, Folder 83)
      - Millay, Kathleen: autograph postcard (signed), New Year's card with poem, and typed letter (signed), 1930-1931 (Box 12, Folder 84)
      - Various: four autograph letters (signed) "Betty", "Jocelyn" and "Mary", 1925-1932 (Box 12, Folder 85)
      - Cocke, Sarah Cobb Johnson "Cousin Sallie": autograph letter (signed); Glenn, Garrard and Rosa: 2 autograph letters (signed), autograph letter (signed); Glenn, Garrard [Fox]: autograph letter (signed); Harris, Mary "Cousin Mary": autograph letter (signed); Schindel, John Randolph: autograph letter (signed); [Family] Priscilla and Betty: telegram, circa 1928-1929 (Box 12, Folder 86)
      - Megear, Virginia Randolph: 10 autograph letters (signed), 1 postcard (signed), 1 Christmas card (signed), 1924-1926 (Box 12, Folder 87)
  - Other Papers
    - Beach: lithograph portrait (Box 12, Folder 88)
    - Doubleday, Doran and Company: publisher's proof, Ad, "Doubleday, Doran Discoveries", 1929. (Box 12, Folder 89)
    - Gurdjieff, G. Pamphlet: G. Gurdjieff's Institute for the Harmonious Development of Man No. 1. (Box 12, Folder 90)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1929 (Box 12, Folder 91)
    - Kesslere, G. Maillard: original photograph (signed) (Box 12, Folder 92)
    - Schindler, Bayard: 15 black and white photographs of Gurdjieff's Institute for the Harmonious Development of Man, Fontainbleu, 1927 (Box 12, Folder 93)
    - The Society of the Army of Santiago de Cuba: certificate of membership [Washington, DC], 1928 (Box 12, Folder 94)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 12, Folder 95)